A Guide to the Records of the Assistant to the Governor for Intergovernmental Affairs, 2013-2021
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Assistant to the Governor for Intergovernmental Affairs, 2013-2021
The Library of Virginia
53523
2.5 cubic feet (7 boxes)
Virginia. Assistant to the Governor for Intergovernmental Affairs
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Accession 53523 was transferred by the Office of the Assistant to the Governor for Intergovernmental Affairs, 14 January 2022.
Historical Information
The Virginia Department of Intergovernmental Affairs was created by an act of the General Assembly in July 1976. Under the Secretary of Administration and Finance, the department served as a liaison between Congress and the President and the Virginia state government. The department monitored federal legislation, reviewed and administered federal grants to state agencies, and provided information regarding federal and state resources. In 1978, the department recommended that the state establish a Virginia Liaison Office in Washington as directed by House Joint Resolution No. 193. In 2011, the name of the Virginia Liaison Office was changed to the Office of Intergovernment Affairs, and in 2013 the position of Assistant to the Governor for Intergovernmental Affairs was created, replacing the designation of the Office of Intergovernmental Affairs.
The Assistant to the Governor for Intergovernmental Affairs is the conduit through which Virginia's Federal Congressional Delegation and its governor, cabinet and state agencies communicate. The Assistant is responsible for monitoring and influencing federal legislation, establishing and maintaining a broad array of federal contacts, facilitating the acquisition of federal grants, monitoring and influencing federal agency rules and regulations and assisting state agencies in dealing with the federal government. The office communicates the positions of the governor's office to the Virginia Congressional delegation and to other participants in the development of federal policy.
Scope and Content
Records of the Assistant to the Governor for Intergovernmental Affairs, 2013-2021, contain records for the administrations of Governor Robert McDonnell, Governor Terrance McAuliffe and Governor Ralph Northam. Records include correspondence, agendas, briefings, conference materials, Governor Decision Briefs, topical summary sheets, and Virginia Congressional Delegataion materials. The majority of the correspondence is in support of Virginia initiatives and priorities and the majority of the conference materials pertain to the National Governors Association. Governors Decision Briefs include requests to initiate correspondence.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Assistant to Governor Robert McDonnell for Intergovernmental Affairs, 2013
Series II. Assistant to Governor Terrance McAuliffe for Intergovernmental Affairs, 2014-2017
Series III. Assistant to Governor Ralph Northam for Intergovernment Affairs, 2018-2021
Contents List
- Series I. Assistant to Governor Robert McDonnell for Intergovernmental Affairs, 2013., Extent: 1 folder (Box 1)
  Intergovernmental Affairs records for the administration of Governor Robert McDonnell include an Office of Intergovernmental Affairs Handbook, 2013. Jeanmarie Davis served as Director of the Office of Intergovernmental Affairs.
  - OIA Handbook, 2013. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series I. Assistant to Governor Terrence McAuliffe for Intergovernmental Affairs, 2014-2017., Extent: 1.4 cubic feet (4 boxes) (Box 1-4)
  Intergovernmental Affairs records for the administration of Governor Terrance McAuliffe contain topical files of interest, National Governors Association meeting and training records, requests for militay appreciation letters, and several reports including those related to Base Realignment and Closure, Commonwealth Transportation Board Six-Year Improvement Plan and Federal Mandates and Regulations Report. May include correspondence, agendas, briefs, reports, and summaries. Some documents may pre-date the administration of Governor McAuliffe (2014-2018), but materials were collected during this administration. Maribel Ramos served as Director of Intergovernmental Affairs.
  - Base Realignment and Closure Report (v. 1, part 2 of 2, Detailed recommendations) - Impacts by state, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Base Realignment and Closure Report (v. 1, part 2 of 2, Detailed recommendations) - Army, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Base Realignment and Closure Report (v. 1, part 2 of 2, Detailed recommendations) - Navy, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Base Realignment and Closure Report (v. 1, part 2 of 2, Detailed recommendations) - Air Force, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Base Realignment and Closure Report (v. 1, part 2 of 2, Detailed recommendations) - Education and Training Joint Cross Service Group, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Base Realignment and Closure Report (v. 1, part 2 of 2, Detailed recommendations) - headquarters and Support Activities Joint Cross Service Group, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Base Realignment and Closure Report (v. 1, part 2 of 2, Detailed recommendations) - Industrial Joint Cross Service Group, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Base Realignment and Closure Report (v. 1, part 2 of 2, Detailed recommendations) - Intelligence, Medical, Supply and Storage and Technical Joint Cross Service Groups, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Commerce and Trade, 2014-2015. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Commonwealth Transportation Board - HB2 Projects, 2016. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Commonwealth Transportation Board - Six-Year Improvement Program (2015-2020) [Folder 1 of 5], 2014. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Commonwealth Transportation Board - Six-Year Improvement Program (2015-2020) [Folder 2 of 5], 2014. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Commonwealth Transportation Board - Six-Year Improvement Program (2015-2020) [Folder 3 of 5], 2014. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Commonwealth Transportation Board - Six-Year Improvement Program (2015-2020) [Folder 4 of 5], 2014. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Commonwealth Transportation Board - Six-Year Improvement Program (2015-2020) [Folder 5 of 5], 2014. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Cybersecurity [oversize], 2015. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Education, 2014-2015. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Education - Miscellaneous publications, 2014-2015. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Federal Mandates and Regulations Report, 2015. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Grants, 2014-2016. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Health, 2014-2016. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Illinois - Federal priorities, 2013. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Library of Virginia, 2014. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Military retirements, 2014-2016. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - National Governors Association - Childhood hunger, 2014. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - National Governors Association - Elementary and Secondary Education Act (ESEA), 2014. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - National Governors Association - Homeland Security and Public Safety Committee, 2014-2015. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - National Governors Association - Cybersecurity, 201. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - National Governors Association - Winter meeting, 2015 Feb 23. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - National Governors Association - Summer meeting, 2015 July 23. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - National Governors Association - Financial analysis, 2015 July 28. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - National Governors Association - Financial analysis, 2016 May. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - National Guard, 2014-2016. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Newport News, 2013-2015. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Prescription drug use, 2013-2014. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Transportation, 2014-2015. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Veterans, 2014. (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Series I. Assistant to Governor Ralph Northam for Intergovernmental Affairs, 2018-2021., Extent: .7 cubic feet (2 boxes) (Box 5-6)
  Intergovernmental Affairs records for the administration of Governor Ralph Northam contain topical files, Governor Decision Requests, National Governors Association conference and training materials, and Virginia Congressional Delegation briefs. The majority of Governor Decision Requests relate to requests to initiate letters to federal government officials and legislators in support for Virginia intiatives and positions. May include correspondence, agendas, briefs, programs, topical summaries. Sean Sweeney, Stacey Brayboy and Craig Fifer served as Directors of Intergovernmental Affairs.
  - Correspondence, 2018-2021. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Cabinet Retreat - Agenda, 2018 June 6. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Governor Decision Requests, 2018. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Governor Decision Requests, 2019. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Governor Decision Requests, 2021 Jan-Apr. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Governors Fellow and Intern Guide, 20. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Governors Fellows and Interns Handbook, 2019. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Grants, 2019. (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Metropolitan Washington Airports Authority, 2020-2021. (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous, 2018-2022. (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - National Governors Association - Management Seminar for Washington Office and State-Federal Directors, 2018. (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - National Governors Association - Winter meeting, 2018 Feb 23-26. (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - National Governors Association - Winter meeting, 2018 Feb 23. (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - National Governors Association - Winter meeting, 2018 Feb 24. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - National Governors Association - Winter meeting, 2018 Feb 25. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - National Governors Association - Winter meeting, 2018 Feb 26. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - National Governors Association - Winter meeting, 2019 Feb 21-25. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - National Governors Association - Winter meeting, 2019 Feb 21-25. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - National Governors Association - Management Seminar for Washington Directors and State-Federal Directors, 2019 June 20-21. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - National Governors Association - Winter meeting, 2020 Feb 7-10. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Northam administration, 2018. (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Notes (miscellaneous), 2017-2021. (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Senate Democratic Rural Summit, 2018 Sept 27. (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Speech - Black Women Talk, 2018 Sept 10. (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Virginia Congressional Delegation, 2018. (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Virginia Congressional Delegation, 2020. (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Virginia Military Factbook (brochure - Secretary of Veterans and Defense Affairs), 2020. (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Year One - 2018-2019 Milestones, 2019. (Box 6, Folder 15)